It's Monday morning.
إنه صباح الاثنين.
In Washington,
في واشنطن،
the president of the United States
رئيس الولايات المتحدة
is sitting in the Oval Office,
يجلس في المكتب البيضاوي،
assessing whether or not
يقيّم أن يقوم أم لا
to strike Al Qaeda
بضرب القاعدة
in Yemen.
في اليمن.
At Number 10 Downing Street,
في 10 شارع داونينج،
David Cameron is trying to work out
يحاول دايفيد كاميرون أن يستنبط
whether to cut more public sector jobs
خفض وظائف القطاع العام أكثر
in order to stave off a double-dip recession.
لكي يتفادى الركود المزدوج.
In Madrid, Maria Gonzalez
في مدريد، ماريا جونزاليس
is standing at the door,
تقف على الباب،
listening to her baby crying and crying,
تسمع طفلها و هو يبكي مرارا و تكرارا،
trying to work out whether she should let it cry
و تحاول أن تقرر ما إذا كان عليها أن تتركه يبكي
until it falls asleep
إلى أن يغفو
or pick it up and hold it.
أم تلتقطه و تحمله.
And I am sitting by my father's bedside in hospital,
و أنا أجلس بجوار أبي في المستشفى،
trying to work out
أحاول أن أقرر
whether I should let him drink
ما إذا كان على أن أتركه يشرب
the one-and-a-half-liter bottle of water
زجاجة المياه البالغة لتر و نصف
that his doctors just came in and said,
و التي دخل طبيبه للتو و قال،
"You must make him drink today," --
"يجب أن تجعليه يشرب اليوم،"
my father's been nil by mouth for a week --
-- لم يتناول أبي أي شيء عن طريق الفم لمدة أسبوع --
or whether, by giving him this bottle,
أم أني بإعطائه هذه الزجاجة،
I might actually kill him.
قد أقتله فعلا.
We face momentous decisions
نحن نواجه قرارات بالغة الأهمية
with important consequences
و لها عواقب هامة
throughout our lives,
طوال حياتنا.
and we have strategies for dealing with these decisions.
و لنا استراتيجيات للتعامل مع هذه القرارات.
We talk things over with our friends,
نتناقش مع أصدقائنا،
we scour the Internet,
نتصفح على الانترنت،
we search through books.
و نبحث في الكتب.
But still,
و لكن يظل،
even in this age
حتى في زمن
of Google and TripAdvisor
جوجل و تريب ادفايزور
and Amazon Recommends,
و توصيات امازون،
it's still experts
يظل الخبراء
that we rely upon most --
هم من نعتمد عليه في الغالب
especially when the stakes are high
-- خاصة عندما تكون المخاطر كبيرة
and the decision really matters.
و القرار فعلا مهم.
Because in a world of data deluge
لأنه في عالم فيضان المعلومات
and extreme complexity,
و التعقيد الشديد،
we believe that experts
نؤمن بأن الخبراء
are more able to process information than we can --
أقدر منا على التعامل مع المعلومات --
that they are able to come to better conclusions
أن لديهم القدرة للوصول إلى أفضل النتائج
than we could come to on our own.
بطريقة أفضل مما نستطيع بمفردنا.
And in an age
و في زمن
that is sometimes nowadays frightening
يكون أحيانا مخيف في هذه الأيام
or confusing,
أو مربك،
we feel reassured
نشعر بالاطمئنان
by the almost parental-like authority
للسلطة التي تشبه تقريبا سلطة الوالدين
of experts
التي يتمتع بها الخبراء
who tell us so clearly what it is
الذين يخبروننا بوضوح تام بالذي
we can and cannot do.
نستطيع و الذي لا نستطيع فعله.
But I believe
و لكني أعتقد
that this is a big problem,
أن هذه مشكلة كبيرة،
a problem with potentially dangerous consequences
مشكلة يحتمل أن تكون عواقبها خطيرة
for us as a society,
بالنسبة لنا كمجتمع،
as a culture
كثقافة
and as individuals.
و كأفراد.
It's not that experts
ليس لأن الخبراء
have not massively contributed to the world --
لم يساهموا بشكل كبير في العالم
of course they have.
بالطبع، شاركوا.
The problem lies with us:
المشكلة تكمن فينا؛
we've become addicted to experts.
فلقد أصبحنا مدمنين على الخبراء.
We've become addicted to their certainty,
أصبحنا مدمنين على يقينهم،
their assuredness,
على تأكدهم،
their definitiveness,
على حتميتهم،
and in the process,
و خلال هذه العملية،
we have ceded our responsibility,
تنازلنا عن مسؤليتنا،
substituting our intellect
مستبدلين عقلنا
and our intelligence
و ذكائنا
for their supposed words of wisdom.
بما يفترض فيه الحكمة من كلامهم.
We've surrendered our power,
لقد تخلينا عن قوتنا،
trading off our discomfort
مقايضين عدم ارتياحنا
with uncertainty
بعدم اليقين
for the illusion of certainty
بوهم اليقين
that they provide.
الذي يقدمونه.
This is no exaggeration.
هذه ليست مبالغة.
In a recent experiment,
في تجربة حديثة،
a group of adults
مجموعة من البالغين
had their brains scanned in an MRI machine
تم فحص أدمغتهم في جهاز الرنين المغناطيسي
as they were listening to experts speak.
و هم يستمعون إلى حديث الخبراء.
The results were quite extraordinary.
فكانت النتائج استثنائية.
As they listened to the experts' voices,
بينما كانوا يستمعون إلى صوت الخبراء،
the independent decision-making parts of their brains
كانت الأجزاء المسؤلة عن اتخاذ القرارت المستقلة في أدمغتهم
switched off.
لا تعمل.
It literally flat-lined.
أعطت حرفيا خط مستقيم.
And they listened to whatever the experts said
و قد استمعوا الى ما قاله الخبراء
and took their advice, however right or wrong.
و أخذوا بنصيحتهم، سواء كانت صحيحة أو خاطئة.
But experts do get things wrong.
و لكن الخبراء يخطئون.
Did you know that studies show
هل علمتم أن الدراسات أظهرت
that doctors misdiagnose
أن الأطباء يخطئون في التشخيص
four times out of 10?
أربع مرات من عشرة؟
Did you know
هل تعلمون
that if you file your tax returns yourself,
أنكم لو قمتم بعمل الإقرارت الضريبية الخاصة بكم بنفسكم،
you're statistically more likely
في الغالب ستقوم احصائيا
to be filing them correctly
بملئهم بطريقة أكثر صحة
than if you get a tax adviser
مما ستكون عليه لو قام بها مستشار الضرائب
to do it for you?
عنك؟
And then there's, of course, the example
كذلك، هناك بالطبع المثال
that we're all too aware of:
الذي نعرفه جميعا:
financial experts
الخبراء الماليون
getting it so wrong
يقومون بها بطريقة خاطئة جدا
that we're living through the worst recession
لدرجة أننا نعيش أسوأ ركود اقتصادي
since the 1930s.
منذ الثلاثينيات.
For the sake of our health,
من أجل صحتنا،
our wealth
ثروتنا
and our collective security,
و أمننا الجماعي،
it's imperative that we keep
يتحتم علينا أن نجعل
the independent decision-making parts of our brains
الأجزاء المسؤلة عن اتخاذ القرارات المستقلة في أدمغتنا
switched on.
تعمل.
And I'm saying this as an economist
و أنا أقول هذا بصفتي عالمة اقتصاد
who, over the past few years,
كانت طيلة السنوات القليلة الماضية،
has focused my research
تركز أبحاثها
on what it is we think
عن ماذا نعتقد
and who it is we trust and why,
و من نثق به و لماذا.
but also --
لكن أيضا
and I'm aware of the irony here --
-- أنا على دراية بالسخرية هنا --
as an expert myself,
لأنني نفسي خبيرة،
as a professor,
و أستاذة جامعية،
as somebody who advises prime ministers,
و كشخص يقوم ينصح رؤساء الوزراء،
heads of big companies,
رؤساء شركات كبرى،
international organizations,
و مؤسسات عالمية،
but an expert who believes
و لكني خبيرة تعتقد
that the role of experts needs to change,
أن دور الخبراء يجب أن يتغير،
that we need to become more open-minded,
حيث أننا يجب أن نكون منفتحي العقل أكثر،
more democratic
أكثر ديموقراطية،
and be more open
و أن نكون أكثر انفتاحا
to people rebelling against
على الناس التي تثور ضد
our points of view.
على وجهات نظرنا.
So in order to help you understand
لذلك كي أساعدكم على فهم
where I'm coming from,
من أن أتيت،
let me bring you into my world,
دعونى آخذكم إلى عالمي،
the world of experts.
عالم الخبراء.
Now there are, of course, exceptions,
و الآن بالطبع، هناك استثناءات،
wonderful, civilization-enhancing exceptions.
استثناءات مذهلة، تعزز الحضارة.
But what my research has shown me
و لكن ما أظهرته لي أبحاثي
is that experts tend on the whole
أن الخبراء عامة يميلون
to form very rigid camps,
إلى أن يكونوا تجمعات صلبة جدا،
that within these camps,
حيث يظهر داخل هذه التجمعات،
a dominant perspective emerges
المنظور المهيمن
that often silences opposition,
الذي يقوم في الغالب بإسكات المعارضة،
that experts move with the prevailing winds,
أنهم يتحركون مع الاتجاه السائد،
often hero-worshipping
في كثير من الأحيان تقديس الأبطال
their own gurus.
لمعلميهم.
Alan Greenspan's proclamations
تصريحات آلان جرينسبان
that the years of economic growth
أن سنوات النمو الاقتصادي
would go on and on,
سوف تستمر
not challenged by his peers,
لم يعارضها أحد من زملائه،
until after the crisis, of course.
حتى جاءت الأزمة، بالطبع.
You see,
كما ترون،
we also learn
نتعلم أيضا
that experts are located,
أن الخبراء يتواجدون،
are governed,
و يُحكمون،
by the social and cultural norms
عن طريق القواعد الثقافية و الاجتماعية
of their times --
لزمانهم
whether it be the doctors
-- سواء كان الأطباء
in Victorian England, say,
في انجلترا الملكية، مثلا،
who sent women to asylums
الذين كانوا يرسلون النساء إلى المصحات
for expressing sexual desire,
عند التعبير عن الرغبة الجنسية،
or the psychiatrists in the United States
أم الأطباء النفسيين في الولايات المتحدة
who, up until 1973,
الذين، حتى عام 1973،
were still categorizing homosexuality
ظلوا يصنفون الشذوذ الجنسي
as a mental illness.
كمرض عقلى.
And what all this means
و ما يعنيه كل هذا
is that paradigms
أن النماذج المثالية
take far too long to shift,
تأخذ وقتا طويلا جدا حتى تتبدل،
that complexity and nuance are ignored
و أنه يتم تجاهل التعقيد و الفروق البسيطة،
and also that money talks --
أيضا أن المال يقول كلمته --
because we've all seen the evidence
لأننا جميعا قد رأينا الدليل
of pharmaceutical companies
أن شركات الأدوية
funding studies of drugs
التي تمول البحوث الدوائية
that conveniently leave out
تتناسى بأريَحية
their worst side effects,
أسوأ آثارها الجانبية،
or studies funded by food companies
أو الأبحاث التى تمولها شركات الأغذية
of their new products,
لمنتجاتها الجديدة،
massively exaggerating the health benefits
تبالغ بشدة في تضخيم الفوائد الصحية
of the products they're about to bring by market.
للمنتجات التي على وشك طرحها بالأسواق.
The study showed that food companies exaggerated
و قد أظهرت الدراسات أن شركات الأغذية بالغت
typically seven times more
عادة سبع مرات أكثر
than an independent study.
من الأبحاث المستقلة.
And we've also got to be aware
و يجب علينا أيضا أن ندرك
that experts, of course,
أن الخبراء بالطبع،
also make mistakes.
يخطئون.
They make mistakes every single day --
يخطئون كل يوم
mistakes born out of carelessness.
-- أخطاء ناتجة عن الإهمال.
A recent study in the Archives of Surgery
دراسة حديثة في سجلات الجراحة
reported surgeons
أعلنت أن جراحين
removing healthy ovaries,
يقومون بإزالة مبايض سليمة،
operating on the wrong side of the brain,
يقومون بجراحات في الناحية الخطأ من المخ،
carrying out procedures on the wrong hand,
يقومون بعمليات في اليد الخطأ،
elbow, eye, foot,
كوع، عين، قدم،
and also mistakes born out of thinking errors.
و أيضا أخطاء ناتجة عن غلطات التفكير.
A common thinking error
يوجد خطأ شائع في التفكير
of radiologists, for example --
لأخصائي الأشعة على سبيل المثال
when they look at CT scans --
-- عندما بلقون نظرة على أشعة مقطعية --
is that they're overly influenced
هو أنهم يكونون متأثرين للغاية
by whatever it is
بأيا كان
that the referring physician has said
ما قاله الطبيب المعالج
that he suspects
بأنه يشتبه
the patient's problem to be.
في مشكلة ما عند المريض.
So if a radiologist
لذلك، لو كان أخصائي الأشعة
is looking at the scan
ينظر في أشعة
of a patient with suspected pneumonia, say,
مريض يشتبه فيه الالتهاب الرئوي، مثلا،
what happens is that,
ما يحدث هو
if they see evidence
أنه إذا وجد دليل
of pneumonia on the scan,
على الاتهاب الرئوي في الأشعة
they literally stop looking at it --
فإنهم يقومون حرفيا بالتوقف عن البحث --
thereby missing the tumor
و بالتالي لا يجدون الورم
sitting three inches below
الموجود على بعد ثلاثة انشات في الأسفل
on the patient's lungs.
في رئة المريض.
I've shared with you so far
لقد شاركتكم حتى الآن
some insights into the world of experts.
بعض الرؤى في عالم الخبراء.
These are, of course,
و هذه بالطبع،
not the only insights I could share,
ليست الرؤى الوحيدة التي يمكنني مشاركتها،
but I hope they give you a clear sense at least
و لكنى أتمنى على الأقل أن تعطيكم مغزى واضح
of why we need to stop kowtowing to them,
عن لماذا نحتاج أن نتوقف عن الخضوع لهم،
why we need to rebel
لماذا نحتاج أن نتمرد،
and why we need to switch
و لماذا نحتاج أن تظل
our independent decision-making capabilities on.
قدراتنا على اتخاذ القرارات المستقلة تعمل.
But how can we do this?
لكن كيف يمكننا فعل هذا؟
Well for the sake of time,
حسنا، من أجل الوقت،
I want to focus on just three strategies.
أريد أن اركز على ثلاث استراتيجيات.
First, we've got to be ready and willing
أولا، يجب أن نكون مستعدين و راغبين
to take experts on
أن نتحدى الخبراء
and dispense with this notion of them
و أن نستغنى عن فكرة أنهم
as modern-day apostles.
رسل العصر الحديث.
This doesn't mean having to get a Ph.D.
و هذا لا يعني أن نحصل على الدكتوراة
in every single subject,
فى جميع المجالات،
you'll be relieved to hear.
سوف ترتاحون عند سماع ذلك.
But it does mean persisting
و لكنه يعني المثابرة
in the face of their inevitable annoyance
في مواجهة ازعاجهم الذي لا مفر منه
when, for example,
عندما، على سبيل المثال،
we want them to explain things to us
نريد منهم أن يشرحوا لنا أشياء
in language that we can actually understand.
بلغة نستطيع حقا أن نفهمها.
Why was it that, when I had an operation,
لماذا عندما قمت بعملية جراحية،
my doctor said to me,
قال لى طبيبي،
"Beware, Ms. Hertz,
" احذري، يا سيدة هرتز،
of hyperpyrexia,"
من فرط ارتفاع الحرارة،"
when he could have just as easily said,
في حين أنه كان يمكنه بنفس السهولة أن يقول
"Watch out for a high fever."
احذري من الحمى العالية؟
You see, being ready to take experts on
كما ترون، أن نكون على استعداد لموجهة الخبراء
is about also being willing
يتطلب أيضا أن نكون راغبين
to dig behind their graphs,
في أن نبحث وراء رسومهم البيانية،
their equations, their forecasts,
معادلاتهم، توقعاتهم،
their prophecies,
نبوئاتهم،
and being armed with the questions to do that --
و أن نكون مسلحين بالأسلحة اللازمة لذلك
questions like:
-- أسئلة مثل:
What are the assumptions that underpin this?
ما هي الافتراضات التي تدعم ذلك؟
What is the evidence upon which this is based?
ما هي الدلائل التي يستند عليها ذلك؟
What has your investigation focused on?
على ماذا ركزت تحقيقاتك؟
And what has it ignored?
و ماذا تجاهلت؟
It recently came out
لقد ظهر مؤخرا
that experts trialing drugs
أن الخبراء الذين يختبرون الأدوية
before they come to market
قبل طرحها بالأسواق
typically trial drugs
عادة يختبرون الأدوية
first, primarily on male animals
بداية، في المقام الأول على ذكور الحيوانات
and then, primarily on men.
ثم بعد ذلك في الغالب على الرجال.
It seems that they've somehow overlooked the fact
يبدو أنهم بطريقة ما تجاهلوا حقيقة
that over half the world's population are women.
أن أكثر من نصف سكان العالم سيدات.
And women have drawn the short medical straw
و السيدات كانوا القشة التي قصمت ظهر المجال الطبي،
because it now turns out that many of these drugs
لأنه تبين الآن أن كثير من هذه الأدوية
don't work nearly as well on women
لا تعمل على النساء تقريبا
as they do on men --
كما تعمل على الرجال --
and the drugs that do work well work so well
و الأدوية التى تعمل بشكل جيد تعمل جيدا جدا
that they're actively harmful for women to take.
لدرجة أنها تكون ضارة فعليا للنساء إذا أخذوها.
Being a rebel is about recognizing
كونك متمرد يتعلق بمعرفة
that experts' assumptions
أن افتراضات الخبراء
and their methodologies
و منهجياتهم
can easily be flawed.
من السهل أن تكون معيبة.
Second,
ثانيا،
we need to create the space
نحتاج أن نخلق المساحة
for what I call "managed dissent."
لما أسميه المعارضة المنضبطة.
If we are to shift paradigms,
إذا أردنا تحويل النماذج المثالية،
if we are to make breakthroughs,
إذا أردنا أن نحرز تقدما،
if we are to destroy myths,
إذا أردنا أن ندمر الأساطير،
we need to create an environment
نحتاج أن نخلق البيئة
in which expert ideas are battling it out,
التي تحارب فيها أفكار الخبراء،
in which we're bringing in
و التي نجلب فيها
new, diverse, discordant, heretical views
أراء جديدة، متنوعة، معارضة، مبتدعة
into the discussion,
إلى المناقشة،
fearlessly,
بلا خوف،
in the knowledge that progress comes about,
في معرفة أن التقدم يتحقق
not only from the creation of ideas,
ليس فقط عن طريق خلق الأفكار،
but also from their destruction --
لكن أيضا عن طريق هدمها --
and also from the knowledge
و أيضا من معرفة
that, by surrounding ourselves
أنه عندما نحيط أنفسنا
by divergent, discordant,
بالأراء المتباينة، المعارضة،
heretical views.
و المبتدعة،
All the research now shows us
تظهر لنا جميع الأبحاث
that this actually makes us smarter.
أن ذلك بالفعل يجعلنا أذكى.
Encouraging dissent is a rebellious notion
تشجيع المعارضة هي فكرة ثورية
because it goes against our very instincts,
لأنها تخالف غريزتنا،
which are to surround ourselves
و هى أننا نحيط أنفسنا
with opinions and advice
بأراء و نصائح
that we already believe
نصدقها بالفعل
or want to be true.
أو نريدها أن تكون صحيحة.
And that's why I talk about the need
و لهذا أتكلم عن الاحتياج
to actively manage dissent.
إلى إدارة المعارضة بفاعلية.
Google CEO Eric Schmidt
الرئيس التنفيذي لجوحل إريك شميت
is a practical practitioner
هو ممارس عملي
of this philosophy.
لهذه الفلسفة.
In meetings, he looks out for the person in the room --
في الاجتماعات، يبحث في الغرفة عن الشخص
arms crossed, looking a bit bemused --
-- المعترض و الذي يبدو عليه الارتباك --
and draws them into the discussion,
و يجذبهم إلى المناقشة،
trying to see if they indeed are
محاولا أن يرى إذا كانوا فعلا
the person with a different opinion,
لديهم أراء مختلفة،
so that they have dissent within the room.
لكي يكون هناك معارضة في الغرفة.
Managing dissent
إدارة المعارضة
is about recognizing the value
تتعلق بإدراك قيمة
of disagreement, discord
الرفض، الخلاف
and difference.
و الاختلاف.
But we need to go even further.
لكننا نحتاج أن نذهب أبعد من ذلك.
We need to fundamentally redefine
نحتاج من الأساس أن نعيد تعريف
who it is that experts are.
من هم الخبراء.
The conventional notion
الفكرة التقليدية
is that experts are people
هي أن الخبراء هم أشخاص
with advanced degrees,
لديهم شهادات متقدمة،
fancy titles, diplomas,
ألقاب فاخرة، دبلومات،
best-selling books --
الكتب الأكثر مبيعا --
high-status individuals.
أفراد ذوي مكانة عالية.
But just imagine
لكن تخيلوا فقط
if we were to junk
إذا كنا سنتجاهل
this notion of expertise
هذه الفكر عن الخبرة
as some sort of elite cadre
على أنها نوع من أنواع كادر النخبة
and instead embrace the notion
و بدلا منها نتبنى فكرة
of democratized expertise --
الخبرة على أساس ديموقراطي --
whereby expertise was not just the preserve
حيث لا تقتصر الخبرة
of surgeons and CEO's,
على الجراحين و الرؤساء التنفيذيين،
but also shop-girls -- yeah.
لكن أيضا البائعات -- نعم
Best Buy,
بيست باي
the consumer electronics company,
شركة الالكترونيات الاستهلاكية،
gets all its employees --
تجمع جميع موظفيها
the cleaners, the shop assistants,
-- عمال النظافة، عمال المتاجر،
the people in the back office,
العاملين بالمكتب الخلفي،
not just its forecasting team --
ليس فقط فريق المحللين --
to place bets, yes bets,
لكى يضعوا رهانات، نعم رهانات،
on things like whether or not
على أشياء مثل ما إذا كان
a product is going to sell well before Christmas,
المنتج سيحقق مبيعات جيدة قبل عيد الميلاد،
on whether customers' new ideas
على ما إذا كانت الأفكار الجديدة للزبائن
are going to be or should be taken on by the company,
يجب على الشركة تبنيها،
on whether a project
على ما إذا كان المشروع
will come in on time.
سيؤتى ثماره في الموعد المحدد.
By leveraging
عن طريق حشد
and by embracing
و تبني
the expertise within the company,
الخبرات الموجودة داخل الشركة،
Best Buy was able to discover, for example,
بيست باي كانت قادرة على اكتشاف، على سبيل المثال،
that the store that it was going to open in China --
أن المتجر الذى كانت ستقتحه في الصين
its big, grand store --
-- المتجر الضخم --
was not going to open on time.
لم يكن ليُفتتح في الموعد المحدد.
Because when it asked its staff,
لأنه عندما تم سؤال العاملين،
all its staff, to place their bets
جميع العاملين، لكى يضعوا رهاناتهم
on whether they thought the store would open on time or not,
جول ما إذا كانوا يعتقدوا أن المتجر سيفتتح في الموعد المحدد أم لا،
a group from the finance department
مجموعة من قسم المالية
placed all their chips
وضعوا كل رهاناتهم
on that not happening.
على أن ذلك لن يحدث.
It turned out that they were aware,
و قد تبين أنهم كانوا على دراية،
as no one else within the company was,
بينما لم يكن أحد داخل الشركة يعلم،
of a technological blip
بإشارة تكنولوجية
that neither the forecasting experts,
و التي لم يكن خبراء التحليل،
nor the experts on the ground in China,
أو الخبراء هناك في الصين،
were even aware of.
على دراية بها.
The strategies
الاستراتيجيات
that I have discussed this evening --
التي ناقشتها هذا المساء --
embracing dissent,
تبني فكرة المعارضة،
taking experts on,
تحدي الخبراء،
democratizing expertise,
الخبرة القائمة على أساس ديموقراطي،
rebellious strategies --
الاستراتيجيات الثورية،
are strategies that I think
هي استراتيجيات أعتقد أنها
would serve us all well to embrace
ستساعدنا كلنا جيدا للتقبّل
as we try to deal with the challenges
بينما نحاول أن نتعامل مع تحديات
of these very confusing, complex,
هذه الأوقات المربكة
difficult times.
و المعقّدة.
For if we keep
حيث أننا إذا ظلت
our independent decision-making part
أجزاء اتخاذ القرارات المستقلة
of our brains switched on,
من عقولنا تعمل،
if we challenge experts, if we're skeptical,
إذا تحدينا الخبراء، إذا كنا متشككين،
if we devolve authority,
إذا نقلنا السلطة،
if we are rebellious,
إذا كنا ثوريين،
but also
لكن أيضا
if we become much more comfortable
إذا أصبحنا أكثر ارتياحا
with nuance,
مع الاختلافات
uncertainty and doubt,
عدم التأكد و الشك،
and if we allow our experts
و إذا سمحنا لخبرائنا
to express themselves
بالتعبير عن أنفسهم
using those terms too,
باستخدام هذه المصطلحات أيضا،
we will set ourselves up
سوف نعد أنفسنا
much better
بطريقة أفضل
for the challenges of the 21st century.
لتحديات القرن الواحد و العشرين.
For now, more than ever,
حيث الآن، أكثر من أي وقت مضى،
is not the time
ليس الوقت
to be blindly following,
للاتباع،
blindly accepting,
للتقبل
blindly trusting.
و الوثوق بدون تفكير.
Now is the time to face the world
الآن هو الوقت لمواجهة العالم
with eyes wide open --
بعيون مفتوحة
yes, using experts
-- نعم، نستعين بالخبراء
to help us figure things out, for sure --
ليساعدونا على فهم الأشياء، بالتأكيد --
I don't want to completely do myself out of a job here --
لا أريد بالطبع أن أكون بلا عمل هنا --
but being aware
لكن ندرك
of their limitations
حدودهم
and, of course, also our own.
و بالطبع، أيضا، حدودنا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)